hey folks read here this is the first in
a series of videos I'm going to do about
the phenomenon of left and right I have
said some things on podcasts and on
Twitter that have raised questions and
I'm hoping to answer those questions so
that people will understand the
framework that I'm working from and why
I've arrived at the perspective that I
have I should say I hear many people
talking as if the terms liberal
progressive and leftist refer to
different factions and that one might
partner with one and reject another I've
been on the left my entire adult life
and I've never seen clean distinctions
drawn between these things in fact I
remember there was a time when the term
liberal had been so thoroughly demonized
by those on the right that I remember
consciously choosing to call myself a
progressive in order to evade the stigma
but there was no change in my
perspective that accompanied it so there
may be slight distinctions between how
people use those terms but in general I
think they're synonyms and should be
treated as such so I've also said that I
am a liberal who wishes to live in a
world so good that I can be a
conservative and that may sound
paradoxical at first or at least strange
but I think it makes a great deal of
sense because the core of liberalism is
a desire for change and if one's desire
for change is an earnest desire to see
things improved then surely there was a
state at which things have been improved
to the point that you would hope to
conserve the structure rather than alter
it at that point you've become a
conservative I don't expect to reach
that place in my lifetime but if we did
the honest thing to do would be for me
to shift positions and say this system
is so functional that we would be fools
to change it so the essence of
liberalism is a desire for change and
change can be about a number of things
in general for those of us on the left
it comes from a recognition but the
systems we find it is systematically
unfair to some people and to the extent
that it's unfair and that that
unfairness is distributed in some way
that is predictable that certain
populations face obstacles that others
don't we could correct that problem and
really I believe we have
a moral obligation to do so I also
believe that we are on a trajectory
technologically and in terms of the way
the population of the planet is growing
that puts us in grave danger in the near
term both of those things suggest a need
for a comparatively radical degree of
change now those on the right are
correct in pointing out that there's
other evidence that says our system is
actually highly functional as we find it
Steven Pinker famously points to a
decrease in random violence for example
and warfare and I believe he has a real
point but I don't think it predicts
where we will end up in the long term
what it effectively is the result of is
the fact that we have created a kind of
artificial growth that goes on decade
after decade and gives people a lot to
lose for engaging in random violence but
because it's predicated on the fiction
that it can go on forever ultimately
it's going to leave us holding the bag
so yes I'm a progressive I'm a liberal
and I would like to see those of us on
the Left who have a rational perspective
that's grounded in science and logic I
would like us to retake the left to take
control of it from people who are using
it as a weapon and to restore a rational
dialogue of progressivism to the
landscape I also believe that those on
the right who are interested in seeing
the best possible system and believe
that we are closer to it than I do
should be rooting for a vibrant left
because it is only the tension between
these two emphases that leaves us with
reasonable governance in other words
liberals tend to be overly enthusiastic
about the idea of change and they tend
not to fully appreciate the unintended
consequences of attempting to fix
problems that are identified
conservatives tend to be very skeptical
of change and when something could be
improved they will often get in the way
of those improvements because they fear
the unintended consequence perhaps more
than they should
it is the tension between these two
things where liberals can
fill in the blind spots of conservatives
and conservatives can fill in the blind
spots of liberals that is the magic that
makes our system function well it leaves
us with change enough to make things
better over time but not such wild
enthusiasm for change that we take a
good system and destroy it in the
pursuit of a perfect one